Register of the Brian Weinstein papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Brian Weinstein papers
1834-2005
90039
Hoover Institution Archives
20 manuscript boxes (7.8 linear feet)
The papers of the American political scientist include writings, notes, correspondence, reports, printed matter, and photographs relating to the career of the black French colonial administrator Félix Eboué in Martinique, Guadeloupe, and French Equatorial Africa; and to the political development of Gabon, especially with reference to the Alar Ayong movement among the Fang people. Used as research material for two books by B. Weinstein, Gabon: Nation-Building on the Ogooué (Cambridge, Mass., 1966), and Éboué (New York, 1972). Includes photocopies of papers of Eboué and of French government records relating to Eboué.
Weinstein, Brian.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1990.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Brian Weinstein is an American political scientist and an emeritus professor at Howard University. He is the author of Gabon: Nation-Building on the Ogooué (1966), Eboué (1972), and Haiti: The Failure of Politics (1992).
Scope and Content of Collection
The papers consist largely of research materials compiled by Weinstein for his books, Eboué and Gabon: Nation-Building on the Ogooué. The preponderance of these pertain to the life and career of Félix Eboué, a black French colonial administrator who served in Martinique, Guadeloupe, and French Equatorial Africa. The Eboué materials contain a large number of copies of official correspondence and reports; they also include personal correspondence and biographical materials. Of note are materials that document Eboué's role in rallying Chad to the cause of Charles de Gaulle's Free French Forces in 1941.
The papers contain a significant number of photographs of Eboué. There are also research materials on Gabon and Guinea, as well as a paper written by Brian Weinstein on the Alar Ayang movement in Gabon.
Arrangement Statement
The collection is organized into nine series: Correspondence; Writing; Research materials; Subject file; Photographs; Sound recordings; Microfilm; Memorabilia; and Printed matter.
Eboué, Félix, 1884-1944.; Africa, French-speaking Equatorial.; Fang (West African people); France--Colonies.; Gabon--Politics and government.; Guadeloupe.; Martinique.; Nationalism--Gabon.
- Correspondence, 1967-1972
  - General, 1968-1972 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Giles, L. C., 1967-1969 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Nixon, E. O., 1967 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Pedler, F. J., 1968 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Taylor, Laurence W., 1967 (Box-folder 1: 5)
- Writing, 1967
  - "The Alar Ayong Movement and a Colonial View of It", 1948-1967
    - Correspondence, 1967 (Box-folder 1: 6)
    - Drafts, 1967 (Box-folder 1: 7-8)
    - Notes and research materials, 1948-1967 (Box-folder 1: 9-10)
- Research materials, 1834-2005
  - Relating to Félix Eboué, 1834-2005
    - Antilleans in Africa, 1931-1961 (Box-folder 1: 11)
    - Associations, 1927-1963 (Box-folder 1: 12)
    - Bambari, 1921-1936 (Box-folder 1: 13)
    - Banda people, 1910-1960 (Box-folder 1: 14)
    - Bangassou, 1923-1925 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - Bérenger, Henry, 1936-1938 (Box-folder 2: 2-6)
    - Biographical materials, 1936-1969 (Box-folder 2: 7)
    - Book of names of individuals associated with Eboué, 1967-1968 (Box-folder 2: 8)
    - Boutin, Elionel, 1928-1939 (Box-folder 3: 1)
    - Candace, Gratien, 1937 (Box-folder 3: 2-3)
    - Catholic church, 1924-1944 (Box-folder 3: 4)
    - Chad, 1935-1940 (Box-folder 3: 5-8)
    - Chiefs and notables, 1903-1960 (Box-folder 3: 9)
    - Chiefs and notables, 1903-1960 (Box-folder 4: 1-3)
    - Chronology of Eboué's life, 1967-1968 (Box-folder 4: 4)
    - Colonial functionaries, 1918-1951
      - General, 1910-1951 (Box-folder 4: 5)
      - Of African origin, 1918-1944 (Box-folder 4: 6-7)
      - Of African origin, 1918-1944 (Box-folder 5: 1-2)
    - Colonial history, 1894-1951 (Box-folder 5: 3-4)
    - Congo-Océan railway, 1910-1961 (Box-folder 5: 6)
    - De Gaulle archives, 1941-1944 (Box-folder 5: 7)
    - Diagne, Blaise, 1914-1932 (Box-folder 5: 8-11)
    - Eboué, Eugénie, 1924-1945 (Box-folder 5: 12)
    - Eboué, Eugénie, 1924-1945 (Box-folder 6: 1-8)
    - École coloniale, 1902-1909 (Box-folder 6: 1-9)
    - Family affairs, 1919-1946 (Box-folder 6: 10)
    - Family affairs, 1919-1946 (Box-folder 7: 1)
    - Family history, 1835-1968 (Box-folder 7: 2)
    - Foreign concessions, 1899-1953 (Box-folder 7: 3)
    - Exposition in honor of Eboué, 2004-2005 (Box-folder 7: 4)
    - Freemasons, 1921-1968 (Box-folder 7: 5-6)
    - French African Conference, 1944 (Box-folder 7: 7-8)
    - French African Conference, 1944 (Box-folder 8: 1-2)
    - French Equatorial Africa, 1909-1944 (Box-folder 8: 3-6)
    - French Guiana, 1834-1967 (Box-folder 8: 7)
    - French Guiana, 1834-1967 (Box-folder 9: 1)
    - Funeral, 1945 (Box-folder 9: 2)
    - Guadeloupe, 1934-1968 (Box-folder 9: 3-11)
    - Guinea, 1898-1959 (Box-folder 10: 1)
    - Historical calendars, 1961-1968 (Box-folder 10: 2)
    - Inspection trips, 1924-1925 (Box-folder 10: 3)
    - Interview, 1943 (Box-folder 10: 4)
    - Kouango, 1916-1968 (Box-folder 10: 5)
    - Lagrosillière, Joseph, 1933-1938 (Box-folder 10: 6)
    - Latrille, André, 1968 (Box-folder 10: 7)
    - Laurentie, Henri, 1939-1943 (Box-folder 10: 8)
    - Lhuerre, Camille, 1908-1939 (Box-folder 10: 9)
    - Library of Eboué, 1968 (Box-folder 10: 10)
    - Locke, Alan, 1924-1931 (Box-folder 10: 11)
    - Louard, Albert, 1922-1925 (Box-folder 10: 12)
    - Map of Oualembou river, 1912 (Box-folder 10: 13)
    - Maran, René, 1922-1966 (Box-folder 11: 1-3)
    - Martinique, 1924-1968 (Box-folder 11: 4-10)
    - Memorial tribute, 1948 (Box-folder 12: 1)
    - Merwart, Emile, 1915-1968 (Box-folder 12: 2)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1919-1940 (Box-folder 12: 3-6)
    - Music, 1932-1946 (Box-folder 12: 7)
    - Notebooks, 1913-1932 (Box-folder 12: 8-9)
    - Notebooks, 1913-1932 (Box-folder 13: 1)
    - Ouabangui-Chari, 1898-1968 (Box-folder 13: 2-7)
    - Panthéon, 1951 (Box-folder 13: 8)
    - Popular Front, 1931-1963 (Box-folder 14: 1)
    - Race and religion, 1930-1948 (Box-folder 14: 2)
    - Report on French overseas territories, 1946 (Box-folder 14: 3)
    - Satineau, Maurice, 1937 (Box-folder 14: 4)
    - Song lyrics in honor of Eboué, 1939 (Box-folder 14: 5)
    - Speeches, 1930-1944 (Box-folder 14: 6-7)
    - Sudan, 1928-1936 (Box-folder 14: 8-10)
    - Tell, Hippolyte, 1922-1929 (Box-folder 14: 11-12)
    - Secret societies, 1928-1930 (Box-folder 15: 1)
    - Uses and myth of Eboué, 1930-1967 (Box-folder 15: 2-5)
    - World War II, 1940-1967
      - Administrative problems, 1941-1943 (Box-folder 15: 6)
      - Antilles, 1941-1943 (Box-folder 15: 7)
      - Boisson, Pierre, 1940 (Box-folder 15: 8)
      - Economic affairs, 1941-1943 (Box-folder 15: 9)
      - Free French Forces, 1940-1967 (Box-folder 15: 10)
      - Rallying of Chad to the Free French cause, 1940-1968 (Box-folder 15: 11-12)
      - Rallying of Chad to the Free French cause, 1940-1967 (Box-folder 16: 1-3)
      - Relations with foreign powers, 1942-1943 (Box-folder 16: 4)
      - Rubber and cotton production, 1942-1943 (Box-folder 16: 5)
      - Vichy government, 1942 (Box-folder 16: 6)
    - Writings by Eboué, 1930-1943 (Box-folder 16: 7-12)
      Scope and Contents note
      Includes notes and speeches.
  - Relating to Gabon, 1860-1966 (Box-folder 17: 1-7)
  - Relating to Guinea, 1897-1967 (Box-folder 17: 8-9)
- Subject file, 1972-1975
  - Niger, 1975 (Box-folder 17: 10)
  - Senghor, Léopold, 1972 (Box-folder 17: 11)
- Photographs, 1870-1970
  - Eboué, Félix, 1884-1944
    - 1884-1919 (Box-folder 18: 1)
    - 1920-1929 (Box-folder 18: 2)
    - 1930-1939 (Box-folder 18: 3)
    - 1940-1944 (Box-folder 18: 4)
    - With Charles de Gaulle, 1941 (Box-folder 18: 5)
  - Eboué, Charles, 1942 (Box-folder 18: 6)
  - Eboué, Ginette, 1940 (Box-folder 18: 7)
  - Eboué, Henry, 1942 (Box-folder 18: 8)
  - Eboué, Robert, 1942 (Box-folder 18: 9)
  - Eboué-Tell, Eugénie, 1935-1950 (Box-folder 18: 10)
  - Gaulle, Charles de, 1940-1944 (Box-folder 18: 11)
  - Angoulvant, Gabriel, 1920 (Box-folder 18: 12)
  - Antonetti, [?], 1925 (Box-folder 18: 13)
  - Bayardelle, André, 1940 (Box-folder 18: 14)
  - Dugagneur, [?], 1920 (Box-folder 18: 15)
  - Merlin, [?], 1920 (Box-folder 18: 16)
  - Reste, Jean-François, 1920 (Box-folder 18: 17)
  - American military mission, Brazzaville, 1942 (Box-folder 18: 18)
  - Cercle amical de Mouila, 1940 (Box-folder 18: 19)
  - Grave of Maurice Satineau, 1960 (Box-folder 18: 20)
  - Gabon, 1950-1970 (Box-folder 18: 21)
  - Unidentified, 1870-1944 (Box-folder 18: 22)
- Sound recordings, 1967-1968
  - One sound tape reel containing an interview with Ulrich Sophie conducted by Brian Weinstein, 1967 (Box-folder 19: 1)
  - One compact sound cassette containing an interview with Eugénie Eboué-Tell conducted by Brian Weinstein, 1968 (Box-folder 18: 2)
- Microfilm, 1913-1925
  - Two reels containing notebooks relating to official trips taken by Félix Eboué, 1913-1925 (Box-folder 19: 3-4)
  - One reel containing notes made by Félix Eboué, undated (Box-folder 19: 5)
- Memorabilia, 1941-1950
  - Framed photographs depicting Félix Eboué, including one with Charles de Gaulle, 1941-1944 (Box-folder 19: 6-10)
  - Framed reproduction of telegram from Colonel Serres, 1941 (Box-folder 19: 11)
  - Medallions, 1950
    - Commemorating Félix Eboué, 1950 (Box-folder 19: 12-13)
    - Commemorating Victor Schoelcher, 1950 (Box-folder 19: 14)
- Printed matter, 1931-1972
  - Monograph, 1931 (Box-folder 20: 1)
  - Pamphlets, 1941-1965 (Box-folder 20: 2-10)
  - Serial issues, 1955-1972 (Box-folder 20: 11-14)